the key to solving problems like this is
to figure out how does the address break
down into offset index and tag bits
conflicts will occur where different
blocks have the same index bits in this
particular cache 256 byte block size
means that there are 8 bits to the block
offset in hex conveniently that means
that the least significant two digits
are the offset and we can safely ignore
those because they are not part of the
index now we need to figure out how many
bits are in the index we have 16
kilobytes and 256 byte blocks the number
of blocks in the cache is this divided
by this and that gives us 64 blocks 64
is two to the sixth so we need the next
six bits here to tell us what the index
is the six bits will be contained in the
next two hex digits so 456 hex we can
write it out as binary this is 5 this is
6 and we are interested in these bits
here so we are really looking for which
blocks of these have the same bits here
those that have 56 definitely will have
the same index bits so we will
definitely have a conflict here and here
possibly but in order to actually have a
conflict it needs to be a different
block this address here does not
conflict with this one here because they
are actually in the same block they have
the same block number so this is not a
conflict they do map to the same place
in the cache but they are actually the
same block so it's not a conflict among
blocks this however is a different block
number that definitely maps to the same
index so this is a conflict 5/5 looks
like this these are the six bits they're
not the same so this block will not
conflict with the one here finally 1/6
looks like this these are the bits that
we are interested in and they do indeed
match the ones of this block so this
goes to the same place in the cache as
this and it's a different block
this is one two three four one six and
this is one two three four five six so
this will also conflict with our block